Guide to the Jack Durham papers, 1850-1985 MS2053
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Jack Durham papers
1850-1985
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS2053
4.75 Linear Feet
Collection contains correspondence, videocassette, slides, articles from various publications, and several artifacts, related to the Chesapeake and Ohio Canal. The material covers the years 1950-75. This correspondence is between Mr. Durham had his friends and associates as they worked to protect and preserve the C & O Canal.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
[required]
Biographical Note
During his lifetime, C.J. S. (Jack) Durham (d. 1991), was extremely active in the Chesapeake and Ohio Canal Association. He worked very hard for the passage on January 8, 1971 of Public Law 91-644 authorizing the establishment of the Chesapeake and Ohio Canal National Historical Park. At his funeral, Colin Ritter described Durham as "... a Renaissance Man--a journalist, poet, artist, philosopher, raconteur, and battler for the wilderness"
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains correspondence, videocassette, slides, articles from various publications, and several artifacts, related to the Chesapeake and Ohio Canal. The material covers the years 1950-75. This correspondence is between Mr. Durham had his friends and associates as they worked to protect and preserve the C & O Canal. There is also material related to Rock Creek Park Day. Durham served as Chair of the steering committee for the creation of this event.
Color slides; Black-and-white slides; Washington (D.C.); Chesapeake and Ohio Canal (Md. and Washington, D.C.); Chesapeake and Ohio Canal National Historical Park; Canals; Durham, Jack; Chesapeake & Ohio Canal Association; MacKaye, Benton
- "Opening of the Canal", article about the opening of the C&O Canal from Cumberland to Tidewater Washington Intelligence, 1850 October 15 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- "Foot Patrol of the C&O Canal from Cumberland, MD. To Seneca, MD" reconnaissance report by Sgt. T.C. Tingle and Pvt. S.H. Hower to Chief, US Park Police., 1951 September 19 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- "Chesapeake and Ohio Canal" too brochures by the National Park Service, Dept. of the Interior, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- "Report of inspection tour of C&O Canal from Cumberland to Weverton, Maryland." Incidental Report of reconnaissance by Pat Grishlcot to Chief US Park Police, 1953 October 19-23 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Letter from Conrad L. Wirth, Director NPS, to Mr. John B. Oakers The New York Times, about Canal Parkway controversy., 1953 December 18 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "McKay backs C&O Canal Parkway Plan" article by Sean Zagoria in The Washington Post., 1954 March 09 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- "Potomac Wilderness" letter to the editor w/ pro-park argument, by William W. Ross. The Washington Post, 1954 February 17 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- "Roadways to Canal" letter to editor by Arthur H. Keyes Jr. and "Scenic Parkway" letter to the editor by Elsie W. Davis, both letters are pro-park The Washington Post, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- "Start of Walking, Camping Trip Along C&O Canal set for Mar. 20" article The Hagerstown Daily Mail, 1954 March 03 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Note by Connie Southerworth and letter by Anthony W. Smith on planning for the Douglas Hike 03/3 and, 1954 March 19 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Two articles in Knoxville, TN newspapers about Harvey Brome going on Douglas hike, 1954 March 07 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- "Washington Column" column by Peter Edson including comments on the upcoming Douglas hike, Ogdensberg (NY) Journal, 1954 March 08 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- "Opposition to Scenic Parkway along old C&O Canal Grows" article in Hagerstown Daily Mail (Evc. Dem), 1954 March 19 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- "C&O Canal Debators agree on Spring Beauty" article by Aubrey Graves discussing Justice Douglas challenge to The Washington Post. "Carlo's Lusty Life ones History" article by Marshal Andrews The Washington Post, 1954 March 04 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- "C&O Canal Hikes to leave from Cumberland to Pass here March 24" article in Sheppardstown Register, 1954 March 18 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- "Beef Oratory Rare at Pre-Canal Hike Banquet" article w/photo in The Washington Post, 1954 March 20 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- "Country Livin'" column by Merby Pasey in The Washington Post, 1954 March (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Editorial comments or letters to editor in five newspapers about Douglas hike, 1954 March (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Committee Logistical plans for hike, 1954 February 01-March 20 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Committee Correspondence with potential hikers and many heavily annotated version of list of hikers., 1954 February 11-March 20 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Committee Press Release by Hike planners, 1954 March 06-10 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Douglas Hike, newspaper articles covering day-to-day progress, 1954 March 20-27 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Douglas Hike editorial comment, 1954 March 20-29 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- "The C&O Canal Hike" article by Jack Durham in The Living Wilderness vol. 19 no. 48 spring, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Douglas Hike C&O Canal Songs annotated, nd., undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Reactions of newspapers and magazines to the Douglas hike, 1954 April 01-08 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Post hike small business (hikers' cast etc.), 1954 April 07-May 03 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Letter from Benton MacKaye to Mr. Robert H. Estabrook, The Washington Post regarding the Douglas Hike, 1954 April 02 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Correspondence and planning for first reunion hike, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Articles, first reunion hike, 1955 March 27-May 08 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Photos, hikers, probably reunion., undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Letters and notes on the formation of the C&O Canal Committee, 1954 March 30-1955 March 06 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Financial records of C&O Canal Committee, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
- C&O Canal Committee letters regarding canal motion picture taken by W. Bryant Tyrell, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Press release, Hagerstown Chamber of Commerce on Canal Planning, 1954 March 27 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Newspaper articles on the Carol Parkway Plan, Post Hike, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Bulletin, Potomac Appalachian Trail Club with article, "Proposals for the Management of the C&O Canal" Vol. XXIV No. 4, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- C&O Canal Committee to C&O Canal Association, 1956-1958 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- C&O Canal Association, membership lists, marking lists, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
- C&O Canal Association, financial records, statements, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
- C&O Canal Association, news publications, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
- C&O Canal Level Walkers, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
- C&O Canal Song, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Reunion Hike correspondence, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Reunion hike newspaper articles, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- C&O Canal Association, by-laws, minutes of Board of Disasters meetings, correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
- "Survey of the Proposal C&O Canal Parkway" 3 annotated oversize pan and ink drawings by Branch of Development National Capital Parks U.S. Dept. of the Interior, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Annotated sketch map of Potomac Basin showing access points for hike, Circa 1954 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Map for Rock Creek Park Day, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- United States Geological Survey/topographic map covering the C&O Canal from Cumberland, MD to Washington, DC, 1943-1953 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Reunion Hike correspondence, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Reunion Hike newspaper articles, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Reunion Hike correspondence, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Reunion Hike newspaper articles, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Reunion Hike correspondence, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Reunion Hike newspaper articles, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Reunion Hike correspondence, 1960 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Handwritten minutes of annual reunion speeches by sponsor Smith, Justice Douglas (1960 - ?), undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Reunion hikers correspondence, 1961-1979 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Pre-park history pre, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- Duplicate copies, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Copied articles, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
- "The Fifth Resource" by Benton MacKaye, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Corps of Engineers studies, reports drawing and correspondence on the Development Plan for the Potomac River Basin, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Potomac Valley Conservation Plan, Confidential by William E. Davies, 1957 April 24 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- C&O Canal Assoc. stands on development on Potomac including dams., 1957 April 25-June 27 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Letter, Benton MacKaye to Robert Estabrook of Washington Post Commentary on the coverage of the dam proposals on the Potomac., 1957 June 18 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Letter, Grant Conway to Mr. Anthony W. Smith, returning a copy of Smith's study of the Potomac water flows, Jan. 23, 1958. Dr. Tisdale, Director of Interstate Commission on the Potomac River Basin, 1957 November 04-1958 January 28 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Newspaper articles, which appear to support a Potomac dam, 1957-1963 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Anti-Potomac River Dam correspondence, 1959 May 29-1962 June 01 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- Handwritten notes on Potomac Dam and water flow [1959?], undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Potomac Dam supporter papers including Potomac River Development Assoc., National Rural Electric Cooperative Association, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Newspaper coverage of flight against development of the Potomac Valley including dams., 1961-1962 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- "Who Wants the Dam and Why" Justice Douglas speech to the DAR, 1962 January 10 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Letter from John Foley of Conneleville, PA to Jack Durham enclosing a newspaper article citing failure of a dam to improve water quality and suggesting this could be useful to rebut corps of Engineer dam proposal, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Letter from the C&O Canal Committee to "My Dear Ms. Secretary" endorsing his action in approving up NHP and expressing the Committee position [1975?], undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Letter correspondence on National Historic Park between Justice Douglas and Sec. Of the Interior Douglas MacKaye, 1956 March 06-13 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Proposal for National Historic Park, newspaper articles., 1956 January 15-February 18 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Jack Durham obituaries, 1991 March (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Support for proposal to form C&O Canal NHP by DAR, nd. C&O Canal Assoc., 1957 June 03 - 1958 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Letters and resolutions on the undesirable impact of a George Washington Memorial Parkway of the C&O Canal, 1957 January 16-May 04 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Congressional Action on NHP Proposal, 1957-1958 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Newspaper coverage of battle to create C&O Canal NHP, 1957-1960 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Newspaper articles, which appear to favor park development, 1957-1960 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Letter from Grant Conway, VP C&O Canal Assoc. to Mr. & Mrs. Frank Love and to Mr. Charles a Myers supporting NHP Status, 1958 January 04-February 03 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- Correspondence between the Williamsport C&O Canal Club Grant Conway VP C&O Canal Assoc. on effort to create C&O Call NHP, 1958 February 04-07 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- "Chesapeake and Ohio Canal NHP Bill" in the report and action bulletin of the Potomac Valley Conservation and Recreation Council, 1958 April 05 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Handwritten notes "Names For" and "Against National Historic Park unsigned" [1958], undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
- "The C&O-Park or Paradox" article in American Forests by Daniel A. Pode, 1959 May 09 (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Correspondence on the NHP bill between Constant Southworth, Benjamin McKelway, Editor, The Evening Star, & Constant Southworth to Rep. Foley, 1954 April 28-1959 May 16 (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Congressional Action on NHP Proposal, 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 28)
- "The C&O Canal" Justice Douglas speech to the DAR urging formation of a National Historic Park, 1960 January 26 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Establishment of the C&O Canal National Monument by Pres. Eisenhower, 1961 January 18 (Box 4, Folder 30)
- Congressional Action on NHP proposal, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 31)
- Handwritten notes Sec. Udall's time concerning land acquisition zoning, and C&O Canal future [1961?], undated (Box 4, Folder 32)
- Notes by Charlton Ogburn to Jack Durham with attachment of 3 letters, which deal with expanding the C&O Canal by incl. Railroad restoration, 1962 March 15 (Box 4, Folder 33)
- Establishment of the C&O Canal National Historic Park, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 34)
- C&I Canal historical events and guides, undated (Box 4, Folder 35)
- Planning the park articles, undated (Box 4, Folder 36)
- C&O Canal Pictures and descriptions, undated (Box 4, Folder 37)
- C&O Canal NHP publications, undated (Box 4, Folder 38)
- Birds and wildlife on the canal, undated (Box 4, Folder 39)
- Williamsport C&O Canal Association, undated (Box 4, Folder 40)
- C&O Canal Stories, undated (Box 4, Folder 41)
- People associated with the C&O Canal; justice William O. Douglas and Orville Crowder, undated (Box 4, Folder 42)
- Impact of proposal it 240 and GW Parkway extension on Canal, undated (Box 4, Folder 43)
- Potomac River population paper and articles, undated (Box 4, Folder 44)
- Edited draft of paper for the Naturalist a geology and native of the C&O Canal area, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 45)
- Public Works Bills, undated (Box 4, Folder 46)
- The Great Falls Park, Virginia Papers, undated (Box 4, Folder 47)
- Newspaper articles on Jack Durham's honors, and letter to the editor, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Poem by Jack Durham's wife Ethel, in The Living Wilderness p. 28, summer, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- "The Rag and Bone Shop" Poems by C.J.S. Durham, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Jack Durham Papers, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Transcribed Interview with Jack Durham for The George Mason University. Oral history program, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Biography: CJS (Jack), undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Miscellaneous unconnected items, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
- "Federal Ownership of Appalachian Trial Urged". Hagerstown Daily, 1957 December 21 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Roadway theft to Glover-Archbold Park, gulletin and letter, 1959 June-July (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Historic Virginia papers and articles, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Conservation/Park/Environment, letters papers, articles, undated (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Unrelated political or government articles, undated (Box 5, Folder 12)
- The Great Falls Park, Virginia, newspaper articles, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Act authorizing the establishing of a public park in the District of Columbia, page 1, 1890 September 27 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- Development Plans for Rock Creek Park unites 2 and 3, Montgomery County Maryland prepared by Olmsted Brothers for Maryland-National Capital Park and Planning Commission, Circa 1945 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- Rock Creek Park Day general information, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- Rock Creek Park Day correspondence, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- Rock Creek Park Day general information, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Letter from Harkean James, Secretary American Planning and Civic Association, to Henry Hopp, Chairman Steering Committee for Rock Creek Park Day, 1957 May 17 (Box 5, Folder 19)
- Letter from Clarence C. Case to Henry Hopp about founding of Civilian Conservation Corps, 1957 May 28 (Box 5, Folder 20)
- Letter from Charles H. Callisan, Conservation Director National Wildlife Federation, to Hon. James E. Murray, Chairman Committee on Interior and Insular Affairs United States Senate, about highways in Rock Creek Park, 1957 July 12 (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Rock Creek Park Day general information, 1957 (Box 5, Folder 22)
- Your Park Guide brochure by Maryland-National Capital Park and Planning Commission, 1958 April (Box 5, Folder 23)
- Rock Creek Park Day general information, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 24)
- An Urban Watershed-Rock Creek and the Nation's Capital brochure proposal for the 6th National Watershed Congress, 1959 May 25-27 (Box 5, Folder 25)
- Letter from Charles C. Glover, to Jack Durham with two enclosures, 1959 May 29 (Box 5, Folder 26)
- Letter from Senator Paul H. Douglas to Jack Durham about canceling Glover-Archbold Parkway, 1959 June 18 (Box 5, Folder 27)
- Letter from Senator Wayne Morse to Jack Durham about canceling Glover-Archbold Parkway, 1959 June 19 (Box 5, Folder 28)
- Rock Creek Park Day correspondence, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 29)
- Rock Creek Park Day general information, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 30)
- Rock Creek Park Day correspondence, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 31)
- Rock Creek Park Day history report by Director of National Park Service to Secretary of Interior, 1961 October 12 (Box 5, Folder 32)
- Rock Creek Park Day general information, 1961 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Letter from Charles C. Glover, Jr., to T. Sutton Jett, Regional Director National Park Service with enclosure establishing Glover Award, 1962 May 25 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Letter, with draft, from Conrad L. Wirth, Director, National Park Service to Charles C. Glover, Mr., acknowledging trust fund for Glover Award, 1962 June 25 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- "Hardy Wilderness a Priceless Asset to Weary Capital" article by Paul Schuette with photo in The Washington Post, 1962 September 30 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- "Rock Creek Park-'A Pleasuring Ground'" article by Ian Kelly with photo in The Washington Daily News, 1962 October 02 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Work Plan for the Upper Rock Creek Watershed, Montgomery County, Maryland, 1962 October (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Rock Creek Park Day general information, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Speech or article, annotated, by Charles E. Randall about first annual Glover Award, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Rock Creek Park Day general information, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Rock Creek Park Day general information, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Draft of presentation of Glover Award to Lathrop E. Smith, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Rock Creek Park Day general information, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Handwritten notes, Circa 1965 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Rock Creek Park Nature Center location map, undated (Box 6, Folder 14)
- "The Townless Highway" article by Benton MacKaye reprinted from The New Republic, 1930 March 12 (Box 6, Folder 15)
- "The Appalachian Trail" article and hand-written outline by Benton MacKaye in The Scientific Monthly, 1962 April (Box 6, Folder 16)
- A.R.M. memorandum on conservation as one of The Three Elements of National Defense by Benton MacKaye, 1941 April (Box 6, Folder 17)
- Letter [from Jack Durham] to Benton MacKaye about hike on Old Rag, 1946 October 28 (Box 6, Folder 18)
- Letter from Benton MacKaye to Jack Durham about White Oak Canyon Trail with enclosures, 1947 May 16 (Box 6, Folder 19)
- Letter from Benton MacKaye to Jack Durham, 1948 October 25 (Box 6, Folder 20)
- "A Mountain and a Man" memoir about Melvin Whitemore Langley by Benton MacKaye in The Fitchburg Mass. Sentinel, 1949 February 02 (Box 6, Folder 21)
- Letter from Benton MacKaye to the editor of The Fitchburg Mass. Sentinel about world Federation, 1949 December-1950 March (Box 6, Folder 22)
- Draft of letter from Benton MacKaye to The New York Times about water resources and conservation, 1950 June 06 (Box 6, Folder 23)
- "Dam Site vs. Norm Site" article by Benton MacKaye about water resources and conservation in The Scientific Monthly vol. LXXI, no. 4, 1950 October (Box 6, Folder 24)
- Letter from Benton MacKaye to the editor of The Washington Post about government decentralization, 1951 February 20 (Box 6, Folder 25)
- Memorandum by Clarence S. Stern, President Regional Development Council of America Inc., about government decentralization, with enclosure, 1941 June 04 (Box 6, Folder 26)
- The Living Wilderness vol.17, no. 43, containing "Wilder as a Folk School" article by Benton MacKaye, and off print of article, Winter, 1952-1953 (Box 6, Folder 27)
- Postcard from Benton MacKaye to Nancy Durham, 1954 February 01 (Box 6, Folder 28)
- Letter from Benton MacKaye to Howard Zahniser about possible Eastern Continental Divide Trail, with enclosure, 1954 February 27 (Box 6, Folder 29)
- "Towpath of Speedway" letter form Benton MacKaye to the editor of The Washington Post about the C&O Canal, 1954 February (Box 6, Folder 30)
- Letter from Benton MacKaye to Jack Durham about paper for International Conference on Man's Role in Changing the Earth, with four enclosures, 1954 November 09 (Box 6, Folder 31)
- "The Regional City and the Watershed District" outline by Clarence S. Stern, 1955 January 29 (Box 6, Folder 32)
- "Natural History Surveys" outlines by Benton MacKaye with sketch maps, 02/23, 28, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 33)
- Postcard from Benton MacKaye to Jack Durham, 1956 January 21 (Box 6, Folder 34)
- Letter from Benton MacKaye to Jack Durham, 1956 January 22 (Box 6, Folder 35)
- Letter from Benton MacKaye to Ethel Durham, 1956 November 25 (Box 6, Folder 36)
- Letter from Benton MacKaye to Jack Durham, 1956 December 03 (Box 6, Folder 37)
- "Life of the Forest-Its Food Chain" handwritten draft by Benton MacKaye, 1957 April 16 (Box 6, Folder 38)
- Cosmos Club Bulletin containing "Concerning Percy MacKaye" vignette by Benton MacKaye, 1957 May (Box 6, Folder 39)
- Letter from Benton MacKaye to Jack Durham, 1957 June 12 (Box 6, Folder 40)
- Letter from Benton MacKaye to Ethel Durham, 1957 June 28 (Box 6, Folder 41)
- "The Morals of Extermination" article by Lewis Mumford in The Atlantic Monthly, 1959 October (Box 6, Folder 42)
- Letter from Benton MacKaye to William O. Douglas, 1961 June 19 (Box 6, Folder 43)
- Letter from C.J.S. Durham, President Chesapeake and Ohio Canal Association, to "A Selected List", about drafting a Wilderness Bill-of-Rights, 1961 July 06 (Box 6, Folder 44)
- Letter from Benton MacKaye to Ethel Durham, 1963 November 25 (Box 6, Folder 45)
- "Early Pioneering in Urban Conservation" article by Mr. Barnes in The Washington Post, 1964 June 07 (Box 6, Folder 46)
- Letter from Stanley A. Murray, Chairman, Appalachian Trail Conference, to Mr. & Mrs. Jack Durham., 1964 July 12 (Box 6, Folder 47)
- Letter from Benton MacKaye to C.J.S. Durham, with enclosure, 1964 July 17 (Box 6, Folder 48)
- Letter from Benton MacKaye to C.J.S. Durham with enclosure, 1964 August 05 (Box 6, Folder 49)
- Appalachian Trail Conference meeting, excerpts from minutes in P.A.T.C. Bulletin., 1964 July-September (Box 6, Folder 50)
- Letter from Benton MacKaye to C.J.S. Durham, with enclosure, 1964 October 21 (Box 6, Folder 51)
- Letters from Benton to Ethel Durham, 1965 April 04 (Box 6, Folder 52)
- Letter from Benton MacKaye to C.J.S. Durham, about Conservation, with enclosure, 1965 July 12 (Box 6, Folder 53)
- Letter from Benton MacKaye to C.J.S. Durham about Durham's note in origin of Douglas Hike on C&O Canal, with enclosure, 1965 July 12 (Box 6, Folder 54)
- Letter from Benton MacKaye, 1965 November 09 (Box 6, Folder 55)
- Letter from Benton MacKaye to C.J.S. Durham, about MacKaye's receiving Conservation Award, with two enclosures, 1966 February 18 (Box 6, Folder 56)
- Letter from Benton MacKaye to C.J.S. Durham, about receiving Conservation Award and designating literary executers, with enclosure, 1966 June 11 (Box 6, Folder 57)
- Letter from Benton MacKaye 07/4/1966 to C.J.S. Durham, undated (Box 6, Folder 58)
- Letter from envelope, from Benton to Mr. & Mrs. C.J.S. Durham, 1966 December 30 (Box 6, Folder 59)
- Letter from Benton MacKaye to C.J.S. Durham with two enclosures, 1967 January 08 (Box 6, Folder 60)
- "Why Wilderness" article by BM in The [Ayer, Mass.] Public Spirit, 1967 January 19 (Box 6, Folder 61)
- "Shirley's Long Swamp a Jewel in Disguise and Official" article in The Fitchberg Sentinel, 1967 February 04 (Box 6, Folder 62)
- "A Prophet with Honor" editorial about Benton MacKaye in The Fitchberg Sentinel, 1967 February 08 (Box 6, Folder 63)
- Letter from Benton MacKaye to C.J.S. Durham, with two enclosures, 1967 March 22 (Box 6, Folder 64)